Philippine CHAMBAULT

322 Palm Street, 95060 Santa Cruz, California, USA (Nationality: French, age: 35)

□ (+33) 6 43 85 29 60 | philippine.chambault@qmail.com | PhilippineCham1 | Researchqate

Presentation

I am a marine biologist with a broad interest in animal movement and thermal biology. I have expertise in quantitative analyses using diverse data sets to examine the movement ecology of marine megafauna species and the role that oceanographic processes and habitat play in species distribution and diving behaviour.

Education

DEPE - IPHC - CNRS - University of Strasbourg

PhD in Quantitative Ecology and Oceanography

• Habitat use of the French Guianese sea turtles using satellite tracking and oceanographic data

University of Pierre et Marie Curie (UPMC)

MSc in Physical Oceanography and Marine Environment

· Conservation and modeling of marine ecosystems

École Supérieure d'Agriculture (ESA)

ENGINEERING DEGREE IN AGRONOMY

· Management of natural spaces, agriculture, agroforestry, animal zootechnics

Strasbourg - FRANCE

Jun 2014-Jun 2017

Paris - FRANCE

Sep 2011-Jun 2013

Angers - FRANCE

Sep 2006-Jun.2011

Experiences _____

University of California Santa Cruz & Greenland Institute of Natural Resources

MARIE SKŁODOWSKA-CURIE FELLOW: PHYSIOLOGICAL AND BEHAVIORAL RESPONSES OF ARCTIC WHALES TO CLIMATE CHANGE

· Eco-physiology, Thermal biology (experimental design on captive whales), Movement ecology, Acoustics

Aquarium La Rochelle

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: THERMAL ECOLOGY OF STRANDED JUVENILE LOGGERHEAD TURTLES

· Satellite tracking, Habitat use

La Rochelle - FRANCE

Jan 2021-Jul 2021

Oct 2021-Present

Greenland Institute of Natural Resources

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: PROJECTIONS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON POLAR SPECIES

· Machine learning: classification (Random Forest, KNN), regression (logistic, additive), climate models (CMIP6)

Copenhagen - DENMARK

May 2020-Dec 2020

Azores - PORTUGAL

Apr 2018-Oct 2018

Paris - FRANCE

Oct 2017-Apr 2018

Strasbourg - FRANCE

IFREMER - MARBEC Sète - FRANCE Nov 2018-Apr 2020

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: HABITAT USE OF JUVENILE GREEN TURTLES IN THE INDIAN OCEAN

• Habitat modeling: resource selection ratio, logistic models, pseudo-absences, predictions

University of the Azores - IMAR

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: INTERACTIONS BETWEEN MARINE LITTER AND JUVENILE LOGGERHEAD TURTLES

• Distance sampling and modeling: physical oceanography, mixed models, drifter data

Greenland Institute of Natural Resources

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: HABITAT AFFINITIES OF SATELLITE TRACKED BOWHEAD WHALES

• Habitat modeling: GAMs, GLMs, oceanographic and climate projection models

Institut Pluridisciplinaire Hubert Curien - CNRS

PHD STUDENT: INFLUENCE OF OCEANOGRAPHIC STRUCTURES ON SEA TURTLES MOVEMENTS IN THE NORTH ATLANTIC

• Habitat use: residence time, state space model, kernel density, biologging, diving behaviour

Centre d'Études Biologiques de Chizé - CNRS

RESEARCH ASSISTANT: HABITAT USE OF THE BOTTLENOSE DOLPHIN OF THE NORMAND-BRETON GULF

RESEARCH ASSISTANT: GROUP SIZE OF THE INDO-PACIFIC BOTTLENOSE DOLPHIN IN WESTERN AUSTRALIA

• Geostatistics & habitat modeling: variogram, kriging, GAMs

Beauvoir-sur-Niort - FRANCE

Feb 2013-Jun 2013

Jun 2014-Jun 2017

Murdoch University Bunbury - AUSTRALIA

Apr 2012-Jun 2012

• Social structure: photo-ID, group size, season effect, boat surveys

Communications _____

Publications (16 as 1 st author, 2.6 articles/year)

2023	P. Chambault , et al. Extremely low seasonal prey capture efficiency in a deep diving whale, the narwhal. (IF: 3.812, cites: 0). doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2022.0423	Bio. Lett.
2022	Heide-Jørgensent, P. Chambault , et al. A regime shift in the Southeast Greenland marine ecosystem. 29(3). 668-685. (IF: 10.863, cites: 1). doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16494	Glob. Chang. Bio.
2022	P. Chambault , et al. Future seasonal changes in habitat for Arctic whales during predicted ocean warming. 8(29). (IF: 14.136, cites: 2). 10.1126/sciadv.abn242	Sci. Adv.
	P. Chambault , et al. Ecological trap or favorable habitat? First evidence that immature sea turtles may survive at their range-limits in the North-East Atlantic. (IF: 4.435, cites: 1).	Front. Mar. Sci.
2021	doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2021.736604 P. Chambault , et al. A methodological framework to predict the individual and population-level	
2021	distributions from tracking data. 11(3). 1432-1445. (IF: 6.5, cites: 6). doi.org/10.1111/ecog.05436 P. Chambault , et al. Predicting seasonal movements and distribution of the sperm whale using machine	Ecography
2021	learning algorithms. 44(5). 766-777. (IF: 3.17, cites: 9). doi.org/10.1002/ece3.7154 P. Chambault , et al. The impact of rising sea temperatures on an Arctic top predator, the narwhal 10(1).	Ecol. Evol.
2020	1-10. (IF: 4.996, cites: 19). doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-75658-6 F. Siegwalt, [], P. Chambault, et al. High site fidelity of immature green turtles (<i>Chelonia mydas</i>) to their	Sci. Rep.
2020	foraging grounds revealed by satellite tracking and capture-mark-recapture and consequences for key marine conservation areas. (IF: 5.99, cites: 15). doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2020.108742	Biol. Conserv.
2020	P. Chambault , et al. Contrasted habitats and individual plasticity drive the fine scale movements of juvenile green turtles in coastal ecosystems. 8(1). 1-15. (IF: 3.6, cites: 15). 10.1186/s40462-019-0184-2	Mov. Eco.
2019	M. Bonola, [], P. Chambault , et al. Fine scale geographic residence and annual primary production drive body condition of wild immature green turtles (<i>Chelonia mydas</i>) in Martinique Island (Lesser Antilles). 8(12). (IF: 2.33, cites: 6). 10.1242/bio.048058	Bio. Open
2019	P. Chambault, et al. Swirling in the ocean: immature loggerhead turtles seasonally target old anticyclonic eddies at the fringe of the North Atlantic gyre. 175. 345-358. (IF: 3.95, cites: 14).	Prog. Oceanogr.
2019	10.1016/j.pocean.2019.05.005 P. Chambault, et al. Distribution and composition of floating litter off the Azores archipelago and Madeira (NE Atlantic) using apportunictic surveys, 141, 235, 232, (IE. 2.12, cites; 23)	Mar Environ Pos
2018	(NE Atlantic) using opportunistic surveys. 141. 225-232. (IF: 3.13, cites: 23). 10.1016/j.marenvres.2018.09.015	Mar. Environ. Res.
2018	P. Chambault, et al. Connecting paths between juvenile and adult habitats in the Atlantic green turtle using genetics and satellite tracking. 8(24). 12790-12802. (IF: 3.17, cites: 18). doi.org/10.1002/ece3.4708	Ecol. Evol.
2018	P. Chambault , et al. Sea surface temperature predicts the movements of an Arctic cetacean: the bowhead whale. 8(1). 9658. (IF: 4.996, cites: 53). 10.1038/s41598-018-27966-1	
2018	M. Nivière, P. Chambault , et al. Identification of marine key areas across the Caribbean to ensure the conservation of the critically endangered hawksbill turtle. 223. 170-180. (IF: 5.99, cites: 18). 10.1016/j.biocon.2018.05.002	Biol. Conserv.
2017	P. Chambault , et al. The Gulf Stream frontal system: A key oceanographic feature in the habitat selection of the leatherback turtle? 123. 35-47. (IF: 2.955, cites: 23). 10.1016/j.dsr.2017.03.003	Deep. Sea Res. I
2016	P. Chambault , et al. Habitat use and diving behaviour of gravid olive ridley sea turtles under riverine conditions in French Guiana. 165. 115-123. (IF: 2.96, cites: 5). 10.1016/j.jmarsys.2016.10.005	J. Mar. Syst.
2016	Chambault , et al. Inter-nesting behavioral adjustments of green turtles to an estuarine habitat in French Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. Guiana. 555. 235-248. (IF: 2.915, cites: 21). 10.3354/meps11813	
2016	P. Chambault , et al. The influence of oceanographic features on the foraging behavior of the olive ridley sea turtle <i>Lepidochelys olivacea</i> along the Guiana coast. 142. 58-71. (IF: 3.95, cites: 36). 10.1016/j.pocean.2016.01.006	Progr. Oceanogr.
2015	P. Chambault , et al. Dispersal and diving adjustments of the green turtle <i>Chelonia mydas</i> in response to dynamic environmental conditions during post-nesting migration. 10(9). e0137340. (IF: 3.240, cites: 21). 10.1371/journal.pone.0137340	PloS one
2015	M. Baudouin, B. de Thoisy, P. Chambault , et al. Identification of key marine areas for conservation based on satellite tracking of post-nesting migrating green turtles (<i>Chelonia mydas</i>). 184. 36-41. (IF: 5.99, cites: 48). 10.1016/j.biocon.2014.12.021	Biol. Conserv.

Conferences

Dec. 2021 P. Chambault, Narwhals in a sauna. NAMMC speaker).	O Working Group on Narwhal in West Greenland (invited	Talk-CANADA
Oct. 2021 P. Chambault , Arctic whales in warming war International Biologging Society (invited spe	ters: demographic and behavioural consequences? $BLS7^{th}$ aker).	Plenary-Virtual
	es narwhals' movements in the Arctic. World Marine Marine	Oral-SPAIN
Nov. 2018 P. Chambault , Argos and genetics reveal conturtles. Argos conference. Collecte Localisation	nnecting paths between juvenile and adult habitats in green on Satellite.	Oral-FRANCE
Oct. 2016 P. Chambault , Distribution and diving behaving Argos. Argos conference. Collecte Localisation	vior of the French Guianese sea turtles satellite tracked via on Satellite.	Oral-FRANCE
Mar. 2016 P. Chambault, The influence of oceanograph turtle <i>Lepidochelys olivacea</i> along the Guiana	nic features on the foraging behavior of the olive ridley sea a coast. 36 th Annual Sea turtle Symposium.	Oral-PERU
Mar. 2016 P. Chambault, Developmental habitat and r breeding green turtles across the Caribbean.	nigratory pathways: identifying key areas to protect future 36^{th} Annual Sea turtle Symposium.	Poster-PERU
May. 2015 P. Chambault, Dispersal and diving adjustment conditions during post-nesting migration. 11	ents of green turtles in response to dynamic environmental th Ecology & Behaviour meeting.	Oral-FRANCE
Apr 2015	en turtles to their foraging grounds: Dispersal and diving mental conditions. 35^{th} Annual Sea turtle Symposium.	Oral-TURKEY
Apr. 2015 P. Chambault , Migration over the Guyana comesoscale features. 35 th Annual Sea turtle S	ontinental shelf: distribution and diving behavior in relation to Symposium.	Poster-TURKEY

Awards_____

2021	Marie Sklodowska-Curie grant, Global fellowship of 3 years, €289,000	DENMARK-USA
2018	Finalist category Biodiversity and Oceans, Young researchers award by the Foundation for the Research	FRANCE
	on Biodiversity (FRB)	
2016	Finalist - 1 st place , Regional final of the "3 minutes thesis" (3MT $^{\circ}$)	FRANCE
2016	Finalist - 1 st place , Best poster at the 36 th International Sea Turtle Symposium	PERU
2016	Finalist, Travel grant for the 36^{th} International Sea Turtle Symposium	PERU
2010	Finalist - Erasmus Fellowship, Mobility grant to study one year in a foreign country (Denmark)	DENMARK

Skills_____

Programming R, R Markdown, LaTeX, ArcGIS, Matlab

Languages French (native), English (fluent), Spanish and Portuguese (beginner)

Supervising _____

Jan-May	Volontary lecturer, Organizing and giving bi-monthly R lessons to students and researchers	Strasbourg -
2017	voluntary tecturer, Organizing and giving bi-monting it tessons to students and researchers	FRANCE
Jan-Jun	Co-Supervisor , Lucie GIRAUDOU, MSc student $(2^{nb}$ year)	Strasbourg -
2016	co-supervisor , Eucle Giraodoo, Misc student (2 — year)	FRANCE
Jan-Jun	Co-Supervisor, Manon NIVIERE, MSc student (2^{nb} year)	Strasbourg -
2016	Co-supervisor, Marion Niviere, MSC student (2 year)	FRANCE
Apr-May	Co-Supervisor, Marc BONOLA, MSc student (2^{nb} year)	French Guiana -
2014		FRANCE
Apr-May	Co-Supervisor , Benjamin MARVALIN, MSc student (1^{st} year)	French Guiana -
2014	Co-supervisor , Benjamin Marvalin, MSC Student (122 year)	FRANCE
Apr-May	Co-Supervisor, Eugénie TESSIER, MSc student (1^{st} year)	French Guiana -
2014		FRANCE
Apr-May	Co-Supervisor, Mégane PINSON, MSc student (1 st year)	French Guiana -
2014		FRANCE

Referees

Mads Peter Heide-Jørgensen

mhj@ghsdk.dk

PROFESSOR

PROFESSOR

• Greenland Institute of Natural Resources, Copenhagen, Denmark

Damien.Chevallier@iphc.cnrs.fr

FRANCE

DENMARK

Damien Chevallier

RESEARCHER • DEPE - IPHC - CNRS, Strasbourg

Jean-Benoit.Charrassin@locean-

ipsl.upmc.fr

FRANCE

Jean-Benoît Charrassin

• Muséum National d'Histoire Naturelle de Paris, Paris

Extracurricular Activities

Water activities: scuba diving (Advanced Open Water (PADI) and CMAS level II, 40 dives), snorkelling Indoor activities: yoga (vinyasa, 3 times a week)

Outdoor activities: skiing (since I am 4 years old!), Horse riding (dressage and jumping for 12 years, 8 years in competition)

Art: drawing, painting (alcohol inks), photography

Travelling